My name is Anakiette. I'm a TA here um
for CS224R and I hope you guys are in
the right place for the Q-learning
lecture. So just as a general overview
what we're going to cover um we're going
to start off by just doing a very very
brief overview of MDPs. Hopefully at
this point um you guys will be somewhat
familiar with the notation and then
we're going to switch over to talking a
little bit about a more um like
controlled or tabular problem where
we're going to be looking at fitted Q
iteration as an algorithm and how we can
build up from the tabular setting to
like learn an effective Q function. Um
and then we're going to move on to
parametric Q-learning looking at the
bias and various trade-off um learning
from TD regression versus Monte Carlo
rollouts and then finally talk a little
bit about some of the practical details
that go into learning effective Q
functions. So this includes things like
the replay buffer that we just briefly
chatted about uh overestimation and how
to deal with the like gradient effects
of TD learning. So an MDP or marov
decision process. Um, so as you guys
have been probably looking at in the
last couple of lectures, we've kind of
defined a kind of framework for us to
look at RL as where we have an agent on
the right hand side that is interacting
with an environment and we define this
framework of an MDP that's defined by a
set of states and actions and also a
transition dynamics function which
allows you to go from a certain state,
take a particular action and go to the
next state. You're also rewarded for a
particular state and action that you
take as well as have different kind of
metrics like the starting state which
tells you kind of where in the
trajectory you're from and things like
the discount factor and horizon which
allow you to kind of um encourage longer
or shorter horizon trajectories where
your horizon is the length of the
trajectory.
In this um lecture, we'll be talking a
little bit about the grid world
assignment. Uh sorry, this grid world
problem on the top right where we have
this little robot that's trying to
navigate to kind of this gem on the top
right. And similar to kind of classes
we've seen before uh our goal is to
maximize the expected return conditioned
on a policy that we're trying to learn
where a policy is simply defined as a
set of actions for each state in this
tabular environment that should be taken
to reach a particular goal.
So in the past couple of lectures we've
been revisiting u looking at a certain
set of objects which we denote as value
functions. Um, so we'll start off by
defining vi of s or a value function
that estimates the expected future
reward where you start at a state s and
follow your policy pi. We also have this
other um useful object called a Q
function where the distinction between a
value function and a Q function is that
now you additionally condition on an
action and look at what the expected
future reward looks like when you follow
your policy.
So both of these quantities are kind of
an estimate of how good um either a
current state is or a state and a
particular action is to give you kind of
guidance for your policy in terms of
what actions I should potentially take.
So if we look at for example a set of
trajectories um as seen here your value
function which is only condition on the
state kind of estimates from a given
state how well if I follow my policy
will I do going forward. Um and a Q
function gives you a little bit more
information where you can kind of probe
a particular action for like an like an
intermediate like an immediate action
that you can take and consider if I take
this action versus another one kind of
what my value can sort of be. Um, and a
useful relation to sort of know in this
case is that your value function that
you've learned on the left is like in
expectation the Q function that you'll
learn on the right.
Another useful quantity that um you
might have already seen is this notion
of an advantage which kind of estimates
how useful it is to take a particular
action a then follow the policy at the
current time step. So the to kind of
understand this we kind of denote this
um we define the advantage as the
difference between the key value and the
value as seen on the bottom.
So to kind of explore how you can learn
a Q function we're going to go back to
this tabular good world environment that
we've been looking at and kind of see
how we can learn a Q function through
dynamic programming. So in class you
might have seen this Bellman equation as
seen um on this slide here which is
defined as the expected reward to go uh
where we look at the transition dynamics
from a current state ST uh multiplied by
the reward at the current time step when
we take a particular action as well as
the MA um added to the max of the Q
value at the next state.
We can then convert this Bellman
equation which gives you the optimal Q
function into an iterative learning
process where we are going to define our
Q function at each time step as
iteratively starting from the Q time
step at the previous time step and doing
this same maximization procedure. So
you'll start off with maybe an empty
grid world which is where your value
function or Q function here is starting
off at zeros at all steps and then
you'll iteratively starting from your
terminal states propagate reward from
your terminal states back to all states
within your grid world. So we'll see
pictorially how that will happen. But
this is like an iterative process that
allows you to propagate value from any
state to any terminal state to all
states within your grid world. This is
kind of the foundation of TD learning or
Q-learning in general and is how we'll
sort of visualize this in the next
couple of slides.
So in this grid world environment that
we're going to look at, we're going to
have again this robot that's in this toy
environment where it can have five
different actions that it can take at
every step. It can either stay in its
current spot, move left, move right,
move up, or move down. and we're going
to be rewarding it if it lands in the
top right square and penalizing it with
a negative value if it lands in this
square in the middle up here. Um,
additionally, we have this notion of a
discount factor to allow us to uh kind
of [snorts]
encourage the robot to reach the goal
state as quickly as it can and not do
like spurious exploration.
So we'll start off with the Q value
function defined as the right here where
for every state it's essentially going
to be zero except for the terminal
states on the right top right hand side
where for the top right corner it is
plus one because it gets a plus one
reward when you terminate there and
negative one for this lava square
and we can then run this propagation for
the Q value over multiple iterations.
And what we'll see is that in time step
two, the sort of states very close to
the top right seem to now get um Q
values due to their propagation and
eventually over multiple iterations
we're able to fill up the grid leading
us to like stable convergence over Q
function. [sighs and gasps]
>> So what is the particular difference
between the Bman equation and this
equation?
>> Yeah, that's a really good point. So let
me go back to where I defined that.
Sorry. [snorts] Um so the Bowman
equation here um as you can see on the
top has no um subscript denoting like
what iteration you're kind of updating
the policy and all it's saying is that
for the optimal policy this like
relation will hold. Um and then kind of
a natural like derivation from there is
that you can kind of do this iteratively
where you start from your terminal
states which already have like a given
reward and you know what that would sort
of be um and propagate information from
that point to then learn the true Q
function at every single time um every
single state and action in your um in
your state space. Um, so this is now
going to have a subscript k + one or k
that represents what iteration you're
going to be um like looking at for each
step. I guess the question or
clarification was uh which one of these
is like Monte Carlo or um uh dynamic
programming. Um so right now we're going
to be looking at a dynamic programming
algorithm. Um, and a quick way to sanity
check that or get a heristic sense of
that is that if you see the Q function
on both sides of your update, that will
generally be a dynamic programming style
of algorithm. Um, whereas for a Monte
Carlo, you will sort of see strictly
only rewards at least for the the
Q-learning updates and value function
updates. Um but right now we're looking
at a dynamic programming algorithm and
that is why we kind of start from these
like terminal states as we see here on
the right and we then propagate value to
all states within our grid. Um I'll
start off by saying that is the state
space here kind of clear. Okay. And the
actions are going up, down, left, right,
and stay.
So these are just denoting each of the
five um like directions. So the Q value
for being at this state and going up is
the top value and going left is the um
value on the left there.
>> The initial state of the Q function just
like something you made up.
>> The initial state of the Q function.
>> Yeah.
>> Um no it's not something that I've made
up. Um so generally um oh sorry I
haven't defined this here but Q0 is
defined as all zeros for all states in
your tabular setting. Um so you
generally typically initialize your Q
function as zeros and then Q1 is just a
single update using the equation above.
Um and the reason that for these states
um the reward is + one and minus one is
because these are terminal states and
then from any action that you take at
these states will result in the reward.
Um and then so this is iteration one and
from there we just do the dynamic
programming update as seen on the top
and we see that the value essentially
propagates from the top state to any
other state in our grid world. All
righty. So in the class we've been
discussing um like notation is something
that you probably are maybe getting
overwhelmed with. So I want to maybe
clarify a few different quantities that
you might have seen and talk about how
it relates to the current grid worlds
that we've been sort of exploring. Um so
the top left here which is V of S is
going to be the value function that is
unconditional on the actions. Um and you
can see that for every state we kind of
assign it a value and we see that from
the top right corner which is the place
where you get a reward you essentially
get a reward of plus one and the
discounting of 0.9 then applies for
every state that um is far away from it.
So you can see that like if you're one
step away you have a value of like 0.9.
If you're two steps it would be like 081
so on and so forth until you complete
the full grid except for the U level
state where you get a minus one reward
for terminating. Additionally there's
the Q star um which is the center thing
that we were just looking at and this is
you can either get this through
convergence of the algorithm that we
were just describing or you can also
calculate it analytically.
Uh finally there is the policy and the
policy is just going to be a
deterministic
um function. Um that's primarily because
for any MD MDP a um without any
partially observability the policy is
going to be a deterministic function
that is defined as strictly the arc max
of the Q function. And as you can see
here it typically has a path towards the
goal. um and is generally the shortest
path for any state in your grid world.
So these are all the optimal value Q
value and policies.
>> So I think for for me looking at this I
think like the policy is pretty much all
I need. So why like what are the
different advantages?
>> Yeah, that's a good question. So you're
saying that okay like maybe these things
seem really like extra like I don't need
to actually learn them. if I learn the
policy, I'm going to be all good. Um,
that's a great question and probably um,
worth thinking a little bit about. So,
what you can think about is that in like
this tabular domain, the way that we've
like extracted the policy is just by
doing an argmax over Q function. Um, so
we needed the Q function to sort of help
us determine like what are the values
throughout the entire state space and we
were able to extract a policy from it.
Um there are also approaches that only
utilize a policy such as policy grading
objectives which you might have explored
in the first couple of classes. Um but
they do experience some amount of
variance issues in your environment. Um
we'll talk a little bit about this when
we go to discuss the differences between
Monte Carlo and TD. But essentially once
your environment ends up being having a
lot of variance either in terms of the
reward or the um the transition dynamics
that results in like policy gradient
methods or Monte Carlo based methods to
suffer a little bit because there's very
high variance in your environment. So a
Q value function can allow you to trade
off that variance for bias and is like
maybe another way to kind of deal with
kind of those specific environment
configurations. So there are trade-offs
to learning each of them and certain
environment configurations tell you to
learn a Q function better than others.
So those are the optimal value Q value
and policies. Um additionally um as I
discussed before there's also a notion
of an advantage which gives us an
estimate of how good a particular action
is relative to the average action in
um the the action that your policy would
essentially take. So for the optimal
policy, the advantage should always be
negative. Um, and the reason for that is
that your optimal policy, your policy is
the optimal policy. So there's no action
that's sort of better than it. And you
can see this in the grid world on the
right where there are actions that are
in red that go towards the LA state, for
example, that are negative in nature.
And all of the actions that are from the
policy are all going to have zero
advantage because they're equivalent.
So yeah, so the advantage is zero for
actions from our current policy. But for
actions that are not from our current
from the optimal policy, they're going
to be negative.
So that is why for every action that the
optimal policy takes in the grid world
on the top right, the advantage is going
to be zero. But for all other actions,
the advantage will be negative because
they can be worse performing than the
optimal policy because there could be,
for example, two actions that lead to
like similar values. um which I think
was like an advantage like an example I
think in
uh
the state on 0 0. So you can either go
up or to the right from this state and
the advantage for both of them will be
zero because they match to the optimal
policy. Um but the optimal policy is
deterministic. So you'll end up picking
one of them as your policy.
So, so far we've been looking at the
optimal policy, but what would it look
like for your current policy or
sub-optimal one? [gasps]
So, here I'm going to show again Q star
of SA and pi of a given S and Q pi of SA
and pi of a given S. So as you can see
this is not a deterministic policy on
the bottom and in many cases actually
does not lead you to the right um to the
right set of actions to take sometimes
even leading to like the lava state for
example and we can see that here the Q
function that's associated with it is
also different from the optimal Q
function. So you can learn a uh critic
or Q function that is conditioned on a
policy that tells you kind of how close
am I to the optimal policy and how can I
improve using that. So if I wanted to
learn an actor critic style algorithm
for example, I could use this um critic
that's conditioned on a particular
policy to tell me what are actions that
might be better than the ones that I'm
taking and use that to update the policy
to then be like one to do one step of
improvement. Um Q store on the other
hand has been converged. So the optimal
policy can no longer be updated because
of that. This is just to kind of give
you a sense of like what the different
notation sort of means. So QI just
relates to the current policy whereas QS
star is the optimal one.
If you guys would like to play around
with some of these tabular environments
you're feel free to do so through the
collab in the PDF that I had shared.
We've been talking a little bit about
these like tabular environments and it's
great to kind of like play around with
these grid roles and see kind of how
values and stuff propagate. But would
something like this actually scale? And
unfortunately, it doesn't seem to be the
case because a tabular value function as
your state or action space grows will
have like thousands or millions of rows
and it will be really hard to learn
that. Additionally, if you instead learn
a parametric value function through like
a neural network or something, you can
allow for kind of generalization to
occur in a better way. Um, so for
example, if you have two states that are
close to each other, either in a
semantic sense or in a literal sense,
you would hope that their Q values are
also very similar to each other. And
this is like a property of smoothness
that you get from the underlying
representation that you've learned.
And what we'll look at next is how to
use regression techniques to learn a
value function with a neural network in
both continuous and discrete
environments. Um so we'll go back to
look at sort of these sort of figures on
the right hand side where the first
figure here is the value function that
is not conditional on state and this
takes in as input the state and outputs
a scalar which is v pi of s. Um
additionally there's now two types of q
functions that you'll like look at. One
is a continuous Q function which takes
in both a state and an action and
outputs a scaler as well as a discrete
value function which outputs for a given
state a vector for all possible like
actions that you essentially have. To be
fair, you could also use the left
representation to learn um the discrete
key value, but generally it's like
advisable to do this as long as your
like discrete space is like tractable
because you have the ability to
enumerate all actions in your space.
>> Yeah. So there's a discrete Q function
and a continuous Q function, but for the
value function, it's kind of irre
irrelevant to the action like space. So
there's only one general
parameterization people use there.
So um for the discrete Q function uh
what you can actually do is that you can
predict the action sorry predict the Q
value for all actions in your space and
then you can um choose the particular
one that you'd want to use. For example,
let's say that there are four actions
like in the grid world that we had like
if we had five actions, you can predict
the Q value for like up, down, left,
right, and stay. Um whereas for a
continuous space, it would be like
really hard to enumerate all possible
actions. So you generally take that as
input instead. So in a continuous space,
you typically condition on a action and
output a scaler. And when you do like an
expectation calculation here, you
typically sample actions from your
policy in order to do so. We have like
this robotic policy and you can see that
um we are predicting values for it at
every single state. Uh whereas for a
discrete um case so you can output a
value for each bin and then enumerate
over all of them when you take an
expectation.
So an advantage of doing the bottom case
is that if you're doing an expectation,
you can kind of enumerate all actions
and you'll get like an exact estimate of
your expectation, whereas on top it's
just a sample based estimate.
All righty. So let's dive a little bit
into kind of how to actually do
Q-learning as a regression problem. And
I'll kind of use the whiteboard on the
right here.
So we're going to be working with
basically
um v pi of s and you can do a similar
derivation for q of s as well. Um this
is adapted from the sutin embarto
textbook.
So um our value um as we've discussed is
going to be conditioned on a particular
state and it can be modeled or it
represents the expected return to go um
from that particular state. So we're
going to then write it now as an
expectation under our policy pi of the
return RT conditioned on our state s.
[clears throat]
So the return can be now like kind of
expanded a little bit to be equivalent
to the sum of discounted rewards. So
we're going to quickly do that.
[snorts]
And this here is going to be uh
sorry I need to take into account uh k
here
gamma to the k
ST t + k and a t + k
uh given st= s. Um so what this
essentially is saying is that from our
current point in time we're going to
look at all of the rewards going forward
discount them by our discount factor
which is exponentiated according to how
many times steps you are away from our
current state and look at what the
summation of that would essentially be.
Uh this as you um asked about is the
Monte Carlo estimate of our value
function um and it's denoted as a sum.
So we can do now some algebra to convert
this into a one-step TD estimate. And
the way that we're going to do that is
we're going to take this reward out of
the summation here and kind of use it to
go back to the value function definition
that we'd had above. So um the first
thing that I'll do is that I'll remove r
of st a t uh when k equals z and then
also apply the discounting here.
We're going to keep the summation again
from k= 0 to infinity. And now we're
going to have one step of
uh we're going to have this summation
again.
Okay, so this part on the right hand
side is just going to be an expansion.
Sorry, this line here is just an
expansion of the line above. We've just
done some algebra so we can get it into
a form similar to the MC um definition
that we've written above. And what you
kind of notice here is that this looks a
lot like a value function. um but now
instead of at the current state it is
going to be at the next state. So we can
now write this as sort of the following
V of S t + 1
given [clears throat] ST = S.
um and by doing so we have now arrived
at our TD um function.
So you might be asking what is the
difference between doing a Monte Carlo
value estimate versus doing a TD
estimate and the main distinction here
is that we're going to be representing
the Monte Carlo estimate as like the
discounted sum of returns over our
entire trajectory. So this is going to
have like no bias.
But instead here when we look at the TD
estimate, we're going to actually
substitute our value function back in.
And this might is going to introduce
some amount of bias because our value
function here can be inaccurate, but it
will reduce our variance because we're
going to reduce the horizon of our
trajectory. So we're going from like a
horizon of h which can be very very
large for a lot of problems to just a
horizon of one. And [snorts] this will
reduce our variance significantly over
the horizon.
Um so that is um the TD learning
estimate that u we've described here. So
notice here that k equals zero. Um so if
I like break up the summation into
uh let me just add this as a step below.
So if I look at the case where k= z is
going to be r of s t + a t
um plus the summation from k = 1 to
infinity of gamma to the k
uh r of st + k
uh oops
uh a t plus Okay.
Uh all given st= s.
Um yeah. So that is how we remove that
term. And you can just do some minor
algebra to convert it from the step to
the one on top. So I'm going to quickly
erase this because I also want to talk
about what an endstep return looks like.
Um so right now like what we did is that
we only expanded this once. But we can
also do this expansion like n times. And
what this will allow us to do is to kind
of trade off between the bias and the
variance. Um so the bias comes again
from the value function parameterization
and the variance comes from the horizon
of your trajectory essentially because
as your like reward function is might be
noisy or your transition dynamics might
be noisy you introduce a little bit of
variance amongst all of the trajectories
that you roll out. So
let's look at what that would sort of
be. I'm just going to quickly grab my
iPad so I don't make a a notation
mistake.
T
So basically what we've done here is
that we've done k steps of rolling out
using the same expansion that we did for
one step and now our uh value function
is discounted by k steps instead of one
step and we are now turning off between
the Monte Carlo rollout which is um
going to be the full discounted sum of
rewards as well as this value function
estimate that we do allowing us to
effectively trade off between
um TD and Monte Carlo.
So let's take a look at how this would
look in a visualization.
So I'll put both of these up on the
slide so we can like compare um one by
one. But if you look at the left hand
side like what we're essentially doing
is that from a particular state we're
going to let our policy roll out until
it reaches a terminal state and we're
going to collect multiple of these
rollouts to do essentially an update by
collecting these rollouts averaging the
reward amongst them to the reward to go
amongst them to calculate this value
function estimate. And that can have a
lot of variance because at every action
you introduce this amount of noise from
your transition dynamics function or the
reward.
In contrast with this TD backup, we're
only going to do one step of unrolling.
But we're going to then use the value
function estimate at the next state to
then reduce the variance of our
estimate. But again, because our value
function can be inaccurate, that leads
to potential issues with bias.
And both of these have some amount of
trade-off.
>> Yeah. So for tabular settings, both of
these approaches should converge to the
same like resulting like equation.
[snorts] But when you go beyond that,
they don't seem to converge to the same
thing.
[snorts]
And again, we're looking at sort of the
endstep returns here as well, where
we're going to allow the TD target to
look endsteps in the future before being
applied. So we could then trade off
between the vias and uh variance here.
Um and yeah, you can look at this table
here to kind of look at what the
trade-off of each of these would be
where the bootstrap depth of TD is going
to be one step, for n steps is going to
be n and for Monte Carlo it's going to
be the full episode. The bias for
something like TD is going to be high
whereas for N steps is going to be
somewhere in the middle depending on how
large your K is. And for Monte Carlo,
you're not going to have any bias at
all. And then the variance would be sort
of the reverse of this where TD has v
has lower variance with nups return
being somewhere again in the middle and
Monte Carlo having high variance. Again,
this also depends heavily on the
environment that you're in. So for
example in language Monte Carlo rollouts
are actually the way that a lot of
people do things because in many cases
your environment dynamics are almost
perfect and your reward signal
especially in domains like math or code
reasoning are going to be perfect as
well. So you don't have to worry about
things like variance of your dynamics.
But if you go to things like maybe
aentic domains or robotic domains a lot
of these factors come back into play.
One other thing that dynamic programming
gives you is this notion of stitching.
And if we look at this like maze
environment on the left hand side, um
you can kind of see an example of like
why this might be powerful. So let's say
that we've collected through our policy
two different trajectories. One that
goes from A to B and another that goes
from C to D. Through this one step of
dynamic programming, what you'll see is
that you can actually find the optimal
path from A to D because of the fact
that at every step you're looking like
one step before it and you can kind of
stitch these trajectories together um to
form what the optimal path would be to
the goal. So this kind of allows you to
get better coverage of your space and
allows these algorithms to potentially
be somewhat more efficient.
Um any questions about this?
Um, okay.
If not, then let's talk a little bit
more about some of the practical design
details that are needed to sort of get
Q-learning to sort of stabilize.
Um, the first thing that we'll quickly
talk about is this notion of a
semi-gradient or target network. And
we're now going to look back at our Q
value estimate that we've been looking
at so far where we define it as the
reward at the current time step plus the
discounted um Q value at the next time
step where you look at the max overall
actions.
So one thing that um what you'll see
here is that the Q function on the left
is going to be the same as the Q
function on the right. But this will
make optimization kind of very difficult
especially if you like propagate
gradients through it. So one kind of
trick that people do use is this notion
of a semi-gradient which allows you to
sort of freeze your target network or
not pass any gradients to it to make
optimization a little bit more stable.
Um and that's defined as this equation
um the second equation that I defined
here. Um, additionally to further make
things a little bit more stable, people
add in this notion of a target network
which delays the updates of the right
hand side to allow your Q function to
regress to a more stable target. And
there are two types of updates that
people kind of use in this space. One is
this notion of a hard target update
where at a fixed frequency you allow the
model to essentially update to the most
recent model that you've used.
Additionally, you can also use this
notion of a soft target update or kind
of an EMA or polyac style averaging
technique which allows you to smoothly
interpolate between sort of the Q
functions that you've seen so far with a
decay parameter. Um, in practice, people
I think try to use the one on the right
that both of them kind of empirically
have been seen to work somewhat well.
Um, and the reason that you kind of want
to do this is that you want to make sure
that when you're doing some amount of
regression, your uh, value function is a
really stable target to kind of like
approach. And some of these things like
removing the gradient on the right hand
side as well as introducing a target
network makes the learning problem a lot
easier. Um there are things that you'd
have to consider in terms of like how
frequently you update your target
network and things like that but for
most cases people have like stabilized
this um as a hyperparameter to around
0.99 for example for the polyac
averaging
typically like when you're learning a Q
function uh you would learn this through
like a regression style of technique
which would look something like this. So
I'm just going to again do the value
function update
uh for to match what we have there. Um,
so on this side here,
this is going to basically be um our
loss quantity.
Um this is essentially just like for a
single sample estimate what our loss
would be and basically we have a learn
network on both sides of our MSE which
will be very unstable to basically learn
from. What a stop gradient essentially
does is that it prevents you from
passing gradients to the right hand
side. So your target is going to be
fixed when you can't pass any gradients
to it but you can pass gradients through
your network on the left hand side.
So in this case when we h when you do
the semi-gradient trick it's only it's
going to keep the same set of parameters
but not pass gradients through it but
the target network is in a completely
different set of parameters that is like
independent of the parameters that
you've learned and you then update them
through this like polyac averaging which
I was showing here. So you have these
sets of weights W prime and W is like
maybe the weights of your current
network and every so often for a hard
target update you would update them or
for your poliac averaging you would
update them like at every step but with
this like soft ratio um averaging
this one here.
>> Uh yes. So this would be exactly the
term that we were looking at here um as
our target. So this is our okay let me
be a little bit more precise. So so
let's say we have like a target value
which looks as our reward at our current
time step
um plus the discounted value
at our next time step. Um so this is
kind of the onestep TD approach that
we're taking there. Um and then our loss
would look something like this.
um is our value at our current time step
minus y
as like an MSE stall loss. Um so this is
what the right hand side sort of
represents. This is like the TD loss
here.
All righty. So we're not done yet in
terms of how to fix the gradients or
making this a little bit more stable.
Unfortunately, there are a few other
types of techniques people have used to
kind of make this converge a little bit
better. Um, the first is gradient
clipping, which you might have seen in
things when you've trained networks in
the past where if you have a gradient
that's too large, which unfortunately
comes a lot of the time when you do
updates like TD, you want to clip them a
little bit to allow you to approach the
to do optimization a little bit more
stably. Um, and here you can see kind of
in this lost landscape for example on
the left, if you don't do gradient
clipping, you kind of go around the
optimal like parameters space. Whereas
if you do some auto grading clipping you
can kind of smoothly approach it.
Um additionally you have you can use
objectives other than MSE to kind of
make this a little bit better. And one
standard thing people have used is this
notion of a huber loss which is like an
interpolation between an L1 and L2 loss.
Uh where it allows you to not be
affected by outliers through like the L1
loss which is this one in green. Um, but
then when you get close to the right um
answer or the right like value, you
allow for an L2 like loss to kind of
kick in and kind of get you closer and
closer to um the target value. Um so
this is like the interpolation that
you're essentially doing by this. Um
there are other things that people have
done, but these are like some standard
things that people have found to help
with learning value functions.
Okay, now let's get to replay buffers.
So
one thing that you might have seen in
lecture either today or last week was
this notion of a a replay buffer which
is a memory structure that you can use
to store past experiences that have been
seen by an agent. And the way that we
like parameterized this is kind of in
this buffer like format right here where
we have these tupless state action
rewards and next states and we store
them indiv individually as transitions
instead of trajectories as a whole. And
the reason that we want to do it that
way is that it allows us to like break
down the temporal correlations of our
data set um and also allow us to prevent
recency bias. So there are two things
that kind of come into play. So the
temporal correlations come from the fact
that at every time step we sample
transitions rather than trajectories and
this can be across trajectories as well.
So I can sample any set of indices
across my entire data set and they can
be from like trajectories one through
like n which are like the max number of
trajectories I have in the data set. Um,
additionally, by like having this like
buffer of like past trajectories that
I've visited, I can avoid recency bias
by making sure that I don't like
overfitit to my current policy because
one thing that Q functions like benefit
from is having a lot of coverage in the
space. And this allows you to not like
narrow down the distribution by your
current policy.
Um, and all of these kind of lead to
better sample efficiency when you want
to learn cube functions and it allows
the agent to kind of reuse this
experience in an effective way. Yeah.
So, this is just going to denote that
your replay buffer can sometimes have a
max size depending on kind of how much
capacity you have. Um, typically this is
not a concern, but if you do, you might
want to either reweigh or throw out like
parts of your buffer as needed. I think
people have explored both RNN and even
like transformer based architectures
like there are works like decision
transformer for example that do
conditioning on long horizons to predict
both actions and values and things like
that and they all have different amounts
of trade-offs. Um for learning critics
or Q functions it's definitely very
feasible to do so. Um for policies in
language for example, we do this by
default. But in other places like
robotics where you might have temporal
correlations in your data, um learning
with history might be actually a more
nuanced topic and can actually lead to
more design decisions needing to be made
to do this more carefully. But yeah,
it's definitely an interesting area to
like consider of like how can I keep in
history like all of the states and
actions that I've seen so far or maybe
even from previous trials and things
like that.
I now want to quickly chat about
Q-learning overestimation.
Um so this is going to follow a
derivation from using function
approximation from RL. Um and again
we're going to look at again the
Q-learning as like um Belman RD backup
as seen on the top. And one thing that
you might notice here is that we have
this like max operation on the right
hand side. um and what happens
essentially if we have some noise in our
Q function when we try to learn it in
this way. Um and this is what um we're
basically going to look at. So um
essentially when we are like
parameterizing this Q function as a
neural network there can be noise in the
estimation that we kind of um incur
[snorts] and we're going to denote our
uh Q function currently as approximate
um which is like the learn
parameterization and Q target here is
like the optimal Q function or the true
underlying Q function and we're now also
going to introduce this uh Y parameter
here that denotes some amount of noise
that might be like present in due to
things like modeling errors.
And what uh we'll kind of see is that if
there is noise on the right hand side
when we're trying to predict the target,
this actually transfers pretty badly to
the left hand side. So what we're
actually looking at here on the left
hand side is kind of what would the Q
values look like after one step of
iteration and how does that differ from
the true target value. So Q approx of S
prime A hat is going to be basically
what we see on the right hand side there
and Q target is what like the true value
would be
and like what we're going to see here is
that if we kind of define even a noise
that is of zero mean like eventually the
noise on the left hand side which is
going to be after one step of update
will have like a positive mean leading
to our Q values to be sort of
overestimated. did. So, this results in
us having to kind of deal with this
overestimation issue when we're trying
to learn our critics. I think one thing
that I mentioned here is that I'm um
that there's like we're going to do a
maximization over actions. Um there
could be issues for example with um
sampling as well. Wait, actually I don't
think that's necessarily the case
because um your true target value um
over all actions might be actually
higher in that case than if you only
look at a subset or of your total
actions. Um so in that case then like
this property would not necessarily be
an issue. Um I think the main like
concern actually just comes from
modeling errors because in some cases
you might actually overestimate your Q
value on the right and once you do
multiple rounds of like dynamic
programming this error will sort of
propagate through your entire um like
state space and will kind of compound
essentially. Let me clarify a little bit
what I mean here by like an error or an
overestimation is actually in the Q
function and not in the actions that
were taken. Let's assume that we can
like enumerate all the actions. we're in
like the discrete space that we're like
working in. Um, and we look at the value
for each of them. Well, what the failure
case I'm describing here is like what
the difference is between the Q function
that we're learning versus the true or
optimal Q function um or Qstar. And what
can happen is that your Q function can
be like incorrectly modeled like maybe
due to some noise is like higher than
what the true target actually is. And
what I'm saying is that even if that
noise has zero mean, when you do these
like dynamic programming updates, it
like propagates to the left hand side
and allows you to essentially get
nonzero mean noise that's being added
due to this like max operation. And this
like essentially propagates through your
entire like state space and makes your Q
value sort of blow up resulting in this
sort of overestimation.
Actually, I was going to go through this
a little bit later, but we can talk
about it now. So imagine [laughter] that
this is our state space. Um sorry there
a lot of um columns in this figure. Um
and we can look at each step what the
value estimate sort of looks like. Um
what I am showing in the second column
here is the difference in the estimate
and the max value the Q function can
essentially have. So you can look at the
left hand side and essentially telling
you what the max at the next time step
could essentially be. And the third here
kind of shows like what the difference
is between the true value and the value
that we want to learn. And if you look
at this like red figure or which is like
typical Q-learning style algorithms, we
can see that there's like a huge like
error bar just because of the fact that
we're like overestimating what the true
value can be and we're like propagating
that through all the states. I'll talk
about like how we essentially fix this.
And one approach that people have taken
is this notion of like critic ensembling
[snorts] where we want to estimate the
epistemic uncertainty of our Q function
using like an ensemble of networks and
we can then use all of these ensemble of
networks and minimize over the ensemble
to kind of get an underestimate of what
the Q value should essentially be. Um
the reason that this sort of works is
that you can imagine that when you
initialize your network they're
initialized in different ways and kind
of the errors that they will get across
states is also going to be very
different. So you can kind of reduce the
uncertainty or u remove these like
modeling errors by ensembling and then
doing something like a min reduction
over all of them.
And this has been shown to be effective
in works like double Q-learning which
I'll show in the next slide as well as
things like offline RL which we'll talk
about later where essentially you can
kind of increase your ensemble size
quite a lot and the distribution shift
is actually mitigated because of like
ensembling pretty heavily and learning
an underestimation of what the Q value
should essentially be removing you from
like getting an overestimation due to
things like noise.
So um the figure that I described
essentially goes through exactly this
and this is from the double Q-learning
paper and like what we see is that um in
the figure on the right despite the red
one red curve here which is like
standard Q-learning having very large
errors just having ensemble size of two
or doing double Q-learning allows you to
kind of mitigate a lot of these
overestimation errors for Q-learning and
makes things a lot stable.
So um for online Q-learning algorithms
you can get away with just doing two and
for most intents and purposes like that
works really well and beyond that kind
of saturates. Um but you can definitely
try to increase that for things like
offline reinforcement learning where
kind of the problem setting that you're
looking at there is that you have like a
static data set that you're sort of
working with and any errors that happen
because you like leave the support of
your current state or action
distribution like allows your model to
like propagate these errors even more.
So there I think being very careful
about the distribution that you're in
kind of matters a lot and you can
increase the ensemble size for like
approaches like edac or sacken for
example that do this. There are ways
that have been looking at this in the
context of language for reward modeling
because in reward modeling you're kind
of going to face similar effects with
like maybe overestimation potentially
and that like reduces performance. So
there have been papers that have come
out that just do things like Laura or
like make sure that you share the
network for like a large portion of your
network. You share a lot of the layers
of your network and have like linear
adapters or something beyond that. And
those are like parameter efficient ways
to kind of learn something like this.